not quite sure why I felt like this was
a particular thing to share but for some
reason it seemed like the thing to do so
there's a particular relatively poorly
formed theory but is nonetheless
intriguing and I think meaningfully
useful and frankly the degree to which
it doesn't have substantial mainstream
traction I think is part of why it might
be useful to more clearly articulate it
and this is sometimes known as
generational theory it was popularized
by Strauss and how about 20 years ago or
so maybe 30 years and let me give you
basically the sense of what I think is
reasonably solid about it and then maybe
the more speculative elements and then
maybe a bit of how and why it might
prove well useful now so to begin with
we have what I would think is a pretty
straightforward proposition and that is
for human beings there is a distinct
difference between first-person
experience secondhand third-hand in but
I'll go ahead and coin is fourth hand
and these kinds of experience happen
because we have a particular
characteristic of being born and then
living for a specific amount of usually
continuous time and then die and so what
that means is that we experience what it
is that we experience firsthand
ourselves but of course there's a
gigantic amount of history that isn't
part of our personal experience that
which is the experience of people who
are relatively contemporary to us most
notably our own parents and aunts and
uncles their you know their parents
siblings and our parents friends and our
own childhood friends parents like that
generation that cohort tends to provide
us with a secondhand kind of
periods so for from from my case for
example I was born in 1971 so I have for
example first-hand experience of the
Reagan years I have first-hand
experience of the Challenger disaster a
first-hand experience obviously of
September 11th the rise of the Internet
the invention and broad development of
the personal computer these are all
things that I have as personal
experience and embodied personal
experiences in significantly richer than
anything that can be conveyed socially
anything that can be conveyed
linguistically so then I have very
limited personal experience of the
Vietnam War in point of fact my mom and
I actually lived on an airbase in
Thailand for about a year and a half
maybe two years when I was very young so
I have a little bit of embodied
experience in that piece but more
fundamentally I have secondhand
experience of the Vietnam War it was
very rich and alive in the culture when
I was growing up and more importantly my
my father served in the Air Force during
the war and it played a meaningful role
in his personal narrative and of course
many of his friends also were part of
the war and effective everybody in that
particular generation was affected by it
in some meaningful way and so in my case
I have a secondhand experience of the
Vietnam War I have direct personal
first-hand experience with human beings
who were themselves deeply impacted at
firsthand by the event so I have stories
that were human individual personal
stories and I have an embodied sense of
the consequence of those stories in a
physical way but I wasn't there right I
didn't live it directly and that
difference makes a difference so then my
grandfather served in World War two so I
have World War two kind of third hand I
mean yes I knew my grandfather and I
spent time with him but meaningfully
less time that I spent with my own
parents
even less time with his siblings and his
friends and and so my experience of
World War two is much more mediated
through pure story I have the stories
that my my parents told me I definitely
have the stories that the culture told
me when I was growing up various
official narratives around world war ii
particularly movies patton and i think
the big red one and the various John
Wayne movies were commonplace they were
alive we weren't that far away from or
to an effect I think right now we're
when I was a kid we were closer to world
war two than kids today or to the Reagan
years or something along those lines
so I certainly was aware of it but I'm
now aware of it as as narrative and not
even really as lived first-person
narrative just very lightly mostly as
the the reflected essence or even
preferred interpretation of the event as
it came through the filtered channels of
many different layers of people telling
the story but nonetheless there's still
a sense of continuity of connectedness
it holds a reality a sense that yeah
that really happened in a way that more
distant past events don't so now we can
jump back far enough let's say the
American Civil War which I now have as
fourth hand meaning I don't know anyone
never have I ever met anyone who
actually lived through the Civil War in
fact I don't know anyone personally who
knew anyone who lived through the period
of the 1862 in 1865 or if I do I am not
aware of that fact certainly the impact
of the American Civil War is now
received by me and in fact effectively
by everybody that I know as narrative as
story and of course at this point now
it's far enough away that the degree to
which the story is only that portion of
the story that has been able to maintain
hold itself in the retelling over a
while which means quite often losing an
enormous amount not only of the richness
of first-person experience but frankly
even have just really what happened we
might say that it's it's transitioned
into myths so first hand is experience
second hand is secondhand third-hand we
might call history and fourth hand might
calm it and the difference between these
kinds of ways of relating to what
happened in the past I think are very
meaningful for the way that human beings
are able to well frankly who we are the
kind of character the kind of person
that lived through the battle of
stalingrad the kind of person who first
person experienced endured the reality
of the kind of crisis that was
associated with that period of time we
just can't you can't get that kind of
character if you haven't had that kind
of experience so what that means is that
we have these college striations of
kinds of experiences that are associated
with the the flavors of experience that
are available to people who are alive at
a given period of time
now I don't want to over determine
because obviously every distinct human
being has a completely singular set of
experiences and that's crucial and
irreducible so this isn't a notion that
we can reduce individuals to groups of
this sort but nonetheless the point is
that when an entire generation of
Russians have to a greater or lesser
extent had first-person experience with
the Eastern Front and an entire
generation of Russians alive now simply
have not had any possibility of
experiencing anything even vaguely like
it that's a difference that makes a
difference all the way down and so now
we get to the second major point so the
first point I think that there is a
difference between first
experience secondhand experience history
and mythology frankly I feel pretty
confident in I mean just the reality is
that the the kind of lessons and the
kinds of wisdom and embodied wisdom that
are associated with having literally
lived through the Civil War just are not
present to people alive now we can't be
we've got all right and our honor
associated with the kind of lives that
we happen to have lived in the lessons
that are learned and coded in our bodies
the hard way so then the next part is to
say well what kinds of phenomena might
we expect to happen as a consequence of
this and here's where things to become
more speculative men potentially more
useful so for example one of the
propositions is if you if you look at
what happened in the 1950s and 1960s and
in particular we look at happened it's a
the Cuban Missile Crisis where you have
JFK facing off with Khrushchev what you
have there is two individuals who have
very distinct first-person experience
with the negative consequences of war
both individuals were physically in
their bodies actually exposed to the
horrors of war and so had a level a
capacity to I want to say empathize with
but in the abstract empathize with in
the abstract how bad that actually is in
a way that almost nobody currently alive
in the Western world has and in fact
they weren't alone there were lots of
other people in their environment who
shared that embodied experience of the
horrors of war and so therefore even
though enormous a number of different
kinds of institutional and even game
theoretic forces were pushing in the
direction of conflict there was another
counter pressure that was a deep
embodied desire to avoid that kind of
result that quite plausibly meaningfully
played a role
preventing that from happening and you
might imagine that today in an
environment where the choice makers
don't have that embodied experience you
look at the leaders of the Western world
right you look at the leaders of the
most of the most powerful world
countries in the world in general
effectively none of them have any direct
first-hand experience with well frankly
even anything meaningful any meaningful
duress
most of the did not even participate in
the conflicts their countries did have
not believed that Putin was first person
to the Afghan war I don't believe that
Trump was first person to the Vietnam
War and you know obviously neither was
meaningfully first person to or at all
first person to world war two which was
the last really serious systemic crisis
that either these countries faced you
know the Chinese have a slightly
different timeline because the the
crises of the Cultural Revolution took
place after the crisis of World War two
and so you do actually have a handful
not many folks who lived through that
you have a much larger handful who lived
through Tiananmen Square which is a
different set of experiences and moral
lessons but still you're looking at a
group of individuals who are
experientially second or third-hand to
anything which is truly truly
existential and intense and so you might
imagine that is these individuals if
they were put to the test of something
like the Cuban Missile Crisis they
wouldn't have the advantage of embodied
experience telling them that this is a
place not to go I mean it's actually in
some sense very simple if you have as a
human as a child actually touched a hot
stove you have a very deeper sense of
why you don't want to touch hot stoves
then if you say watched your sister
touch a hot stove then if you heard your
sister tell don't touch a hot stove then
if you you know heard from a teacher at
school say don't touch hot stoves like
the distance from invited experience to
mythology or fourth hand experience is
enormous and the ability of that the
potency of that experience to shape your
choices is significant so we can say
that the second layer that we might we
might deduce that deeply shared which is
to say large numbers of people in a
given point in time in a given society
who share similar levels of intensity of
embodied experience the specific
qualities may be quite different but the
the basic flavor of don't do that for
example is relatively shared we should
expect to have political and
sociological consequences and then the
lack thereof also to have political and
sociological consequences so then we get
to the third and then by far the most
speculative point which is you say okay
then can we use that to to generate some
expectations is there is there perhaps a
reason to believe that when you find
yourself in a moment like now we're
effectively all of the choice makers
around the world are third hand dealing
with the last major of real consequences
the crisis of real serious existential
conflict and many of their
constituencies are now at fourth hand
which is one of the things that we see
in social media for example with
Millennials we have no awareness of the
real feeling of actual crisis might
there not be reckless might they not be
not fully able to embody a wisdom about
why people don't like these kinds of
things and therefore be more willing to
push be more willing to take risks be
more willing to play a form of
brinksmanship with themselves and with
each others that is in fact
categorically unwise and therefore of
course might we then find that this kind
of circumstance where entire leader
ship groups in society are willing to
take risks are willing to be reckless
that if that happens to be the case then
we would expect to find bad choices to
be made and we would expect to find
tipping points to be tipped over and
then we would expect to find that
leading to crisis so this thing would be
the the final point is to propose that
it is precisely the degree to which
crisis delivers embodied wisdom to
enough people in society that the
society itself in some sense carried
that it carries that embodied wisdom and
therefore hangs together studiously
avoids the kinds of things like
polarization and squabbling and sort of
a ruthless struggle over small victories
and self aggrandizement but rather
focuses on maintaining the integrity of
the whole because they know that those
kinds of breakdowns lead to very bad
results all the way down to their bones
and that is precisely the degree to
which we have grown distant from those
times and have moved from embodied
wisdom to stories of our elders to
history books to mythology that we find
ourselves vulnerable to making those bad
choices and thereby once again finding
ourselves falling into the pit of those
crises now it's not clear whether the
story is true worse it's not clear even
if this is story if the story is true
how we might be able to use it to guide
our own behaviors it may very well be
that it's nothing more than a thing that
we can witness as we drive our car off
the cliff never having done it before
and therefore not knowing how bad that
can be but perhaps we can hope that we
have some capacity to learn in some way
so that we
can find ways to more fully and more
effectively build an embodied wisdom so
that we can as a society make good
choices that don't involve constantly
touching the hot stove